<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='client.filepoller' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status="CLOSED">
   <topic>
      You can publish messages by putting files on a certain location in the file system.
   </topic>

   <description>
      This is a native plugin which is listening on a certain directory in the file system. 
      It detects by polling on the directory if a new file has arrived. Once the plugin assumes it has
      completely written, it will read its contents and publish them.
      
      <ul>
         <li>The Poller is running as a native xmlBlaster plugin</li>
         <li>Every registered Poller is listening on exactly one single directory</li>
         <li>The polling interval is expressed in ms and is configurable</li>
         <li>All files in a directory on which a Poller instance is listening, are published on 
             a single configurable topic.</li>
         <li>It is possible to specify a filter for the file name, then only the files matching the filter
             will be processed by the current plugin instance. 
         </li>
         <li>It is possible to have several plugins polling for the same directory provided they all have
             a filter specified. The choice of the filters must be such to avoid that the same file will 
             match more than one filter. If the user does not ensure that, unpredicted behavior will result. 
         </li>

         <li>After a successful publish of the content of a file, the file is removed from the file system.
              Alternatively, if a 'sent' directory is specified in the configuration, processed
              files will be moved to that destination. If for some reason it is not possible to 
              move the file to that direction (for example if necessary rights are missing), then the
              plugin will continue to poll but will not process any file anymore until the problem has
              been manually removed.
         </li>
         <li>It is possible to configure a maximum file size. Files bigger than the specified size are not
             published. If a 'discarded' directory is specified in the properties, then the file will be 
             moved to that directory, otherwise it will be deleted.
         </li>
         <li>
            When moving files, wether to the 'sent' or 'discarded' directories, if a file with the same
            relative name already exists, it is overwritten.
         </li>
         <li>
            Detection of 'file ready for publishing': 
            <p>
            If <i>lockExtention</i> is specified in the plugin configuration, then publishing of a file is
            controlled by a <i>lock</i> file. 
            This means that if you specified <i>*.lck</i> as the <i>lockExtention</i>, and want to publish
            a file called <i>someFile.gif</i>, then the publishing of the file will be inhibited until a 
            file <i>someFile.gif.lck</i> will be present in the directory.
            </p>
            <p>
            The plugin will wait <i>delaySinceLastFileChange</i> milliseconds since 
            the last modification of the file to be published (date and size are checked) before 
            processing anyway. This way, by choosing a sufficiently long <i>delaySinceLastFileChange</i>
            it is possible to work in an <i>optimistic</i> way without any lock file. 
            </p>
            <p>
            Note however that this <i>optimistic</i> publishing is not to 100% safe. Suppose the writing of
            the file to be published is stalled for a time which is longer than what specified in
            <i>delaySinceLastFileChange</i>, then the file will be published in its incomplete state.
            </p>        
         </li>
         <li>
           If permissions to read the directory are missing or xmlBlaster has no read rights on a 
           specific file, or if an IO exception occurs when reading a file or trying to delete or move
           a file, an error is reported (logged) and the plugin does temporarly stop working.
           (to ensure correct sequence). The plugin continues however to poll and when the rights are 
           manually fixed, it continues working again.
         </li>
         <li>
           To be able to track the message origin, filename and date are sent in the client properties as:
           <ul>
              <li><i>_fileName</i></li> (the relative file name as a String)
              <li><i>_fileDate</i></li> (the timestamp of the file in ms as a long)
           </ul>
         </li>
         <li>
           To listen to different directories and/or to publish on different topics you need to configure different
           plugins. When doing so assign to each plugin a different id (this is actually a general requirement for the
           plugins).
         </li>
       </ul>
   </description>


   <example lang="any" type="HTML">
      <p id="regex" class="celltitel">Testing your filter pattern</p>
      <p>You have two options to test your regular expression or your 'simple' filter in your configuration.</p>
      <p>First, you can use the  <a href="admin.jmx.html#jconsole" target="others"><code>jconsole</code> (see admin.jmx requirement)</a>
      to test your filter pattern. Go to the <code>MBean -> org.xmlBlaster -> node -> [your cluster name] -> service -> FilePollerPlugin[xxx]</code>
      area. Here you can adjust all settings dynamically and test the settings under the tab <code>Operations</code> by clicking the
      <code>triggerScan</code> button.
      </p>
      <p>Further you can test the pattern on command line:</p>

<pre class="BORDER">
 java org.xmlBlaster.client.filepoller.DirectoryManager -path /tmp/filepoller -filter "*.xml" -filterType simple 

 java org.xmlBlaster.client.filepoller.DirectoryManager -path /tmp/filepoller -filter "hi.*\.xml" -filterType regex 
</pre>

   </example>


   <configuration where="server">
      <p>
         The plugin is configured in the xmlBlasterPlugins.xml configuration file. Here an example where
         all properties are used:
<pre>
<![CDATA[
  <xmlBlaster>
    ...

     <plugin id='FilePollerPlugin' className='org.xmlBlaster.client.filepoller.FilePollerPlugin'>
        <attribute id='directoryName'>/tmp/filePoller</attribute>
        <attribute id='topicName'>poller.test</attribute>
        <attribute id='publishKey'><key oid='poller.test'><poller><test/></poller></key></attribute>
        <attribute id='publishQos'><qos><expiration lifeTime='4000'/></qos></attribute>
        <attribute id='connectQos'></attribute>
        <attribute id='maximumFileSize'>10000000</attribute>
        <attribute id='delaySinceLastFileChange'>10000</attribute>
        <attribute id='pollInterval'>2000</attribute>

        <attribute id='loginName'>fritz</attribute>
        <attribute id='password'>secret</attribute>
        <attribute id='sent'>Sent</attribute>
        <attribute id='discarded'>Discarded</attribute>
        <attribute id='fileFilter'></attribute>
        <attribute id='lockExtention'>*.lck</attribute>
        <attribute id='filterType'>simple</attribute>

        <action do='LOAD' onStartupRunlevel='9' sequence='6' onFail='resource.configuration.pluginFailed'/>
        <action do='STOP' onShutdownRunlevel='6' sequence='5'/>
     </plugin>
   ...

 </xmlBlaster>
]]>
</pre>
and here a minimalistic one:

<pre>
<![CDATA[
  <xmlBlaster>
    ...

     <plugin id='FilePollerPlugin' className='org.xmlBlaster.client.filepoller.FilePollerPlugin'>
        <attribute id='directoryName'>/tmp/filePoller</attribute>
        <attribute id='topicName'>poller.test</attribute>
        <!-- determines on which level to start/shutdown the plugin and what to do in case of an exception -->
        <action do='LOAD' onStartupRunlevel='9' sequence='6' onFail='resource.configuration.pluginFailed'/>
        <action do='STOP' onShutdownRunlevel='6' sequence='5'/>
     </plugin>
   ...

 </xmlBlaster>
]]>
</pre>
 </p>

 and here a more detailed description about each attribute:

    <table border="1">
       <tr>
         <th>id (name)</th>
         <th>type</th>
         <th>default value</th>
         <th>Comment</th>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>directoryName</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>mandatory</b>: The name of the directory on which this plugin instance will listen.
            If the directory does not exist, one will be created. You can specify an absolute name or
            a relative one. A relative one is based on the <i>${user.home}</i>.
         </td>
       </tr>

       <tr>
         <td>topicName</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>mandatory unless <i>publishKey</i> defined</b>. If both are specified this attribute is
         ignored and a warning is logged. This is the name of the topic on which to publish (the oid). 
         </td>
       </tr>

       <tr>
         <td>publishKey</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b> unless <i>topicName</i> has not been specified in which case it is mandatory.
         If you need to specify a more complex <a href="interface.publish.html">key</a> for the publishing 
         (for example to make it searcheable)
         of the messages you can specify it here. Note that you can only specify one single key which will
         be used for all messages published by this plugin. If you need to differentiate you can use
         more plugins.
         </td>
       </tr>

       <tr>
         <td>publishQos</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>.
         If you need to specify a more complex <a href="interface.publish.html">qos</a> for the publishing 
         you can specify it here. Note that you can only specify one single qos which will
         be used for all messages published by this plugin. If you need to differentiate you can use
         more plugins.
         </td>
       </tr>

       <tr>
         <td>connectQos</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>. If you need to specify more complex 
         <a href="interface.connect.html">connection behavior</a> you can do it here. Note however that
         this is a plugin which per default uses the <a href="protocol.local.html">local protocol</a>.
         </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>loginName</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>'_' + id of plugin</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>. If the id of the plugin is <i>poller1</i>, then the default <i>loginName</i>
         is <i>_poller1</i>. If you specify a <i>connectQos</i>, then this attribute is ignored.
         </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>password</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>. This is the password to be used to authenticate the <i>loginName</i>.
         If you specify a <i>connectQos</i>, then this attribute is ignored.
         </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>pollInterval</td>
         <td>long</td>
         <td>2000</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>:  The time in milliseconds the plugin sleeps between each poll sweep. This
         time is also the one used to retry an action which has failed (reading, deleting or moving a 
         file).
         </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>delaySinceLastFileChange</td>
         <td>long</td>
         <td>10000</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: This is the time expressed in milliseconds which the plugin will wait
         before publishing a file after its latest detected change. The plugin detects changes on
         discrete times (every time it polls), so the acurancy is never better than what specified in
         <i>pollInterval</i>. A file is considered to have changed either if its size has changed or 
         its date. The plugin always waits what specified here even when using a lock file. So if you 
         always control your publishes with a locking file you can set this attribute to zero to
         avoid delay.
         </td>
       </tr>


       <tr>
         <td>maximumFileSize</td>
         <td>long</td>
         <td>10000000</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: The maximum file size expressed in bytes to be allowed to be published. If
         the file exceeds this size, then it is not published. It is either deleted or moved to the 
         directory specified in the <i>discarded</i> attribute.
         </td>
       </tr>

       <tr>
         <td>fileFilter</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: If you want this plugin to be listening only on a specified filename extention
         you can specify it here. Let's say you only want files with the gif extention to be sent, then you 
         specify <i>*.gif</i>. If something is specified here, files on the directory not matching this
         pattern are left untouched and are not published.
         </td>
       </tr>

       <tr>
         <td>lockExtention</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: If you want to use the locking approach you need to specify here the extention
         of the lock files. The syntax is of the kind <i>*.lck</i>, i.e. the first character is a '*'.
         </td>
       </tr>

       <tr>
         <td>sent</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: If nothing is specified here, files are deleted after having been published.
         If something is specified here it is assumed to be a directory and files published are moved to this
         location. If the directory does not exist, one is created once the plugin is initialized. 
         You can either specify an absolute or a relative directory name. Relative names are put in the
         directory specified in the <i>directoryName</i> attribute.
         </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>discarded</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>null</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: If nothing is specified here, files which are too big to be 
         published are deleted.
         If something is specified it is assumed to be a directory and the files which are too bif are 
         moved to this location. 
         If the directory does not exist, one is created once the plugin is initialized. 
         You can either specify an absolute or a relative directory name. Relative names are put in the
         directory specified in the <i>directoryName</i> attribute.
         </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>filterType</td>
         <td>String</td>
         <td>simple</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: If nothing is specified here, 'simple' is assumed. Valid types are 'simple' and 
                'regex'. This attribute decides which filter to use when processing both the fileFilter.
                If you choose 'simple' then you can specify filters of the kind '*.xml' which are very simple to be used but
                somehow limited if you want more advanced things to be done. The type 'regex' allows you to use regex 
                syntax for the fileFilter. Note that <i>lockExtention</i> is not affected by this flag and is always considered
                of type 'simple'.
         </td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
         <td>copyOnMove</td>
         <td>boolean</td>
         <td>true</td>
         <td><b>optional</b>: This flag has only effect if <b>sent</b> or <b>discarded</b> have been defined. If this 
             flag is set to false then the file will be simply moved (or renamed). This is fast but it does not 
             work on all OS systems. Particularly on non-local file systems this is known to fail.
             Leaving this flag <i>true</i> (default) forces a complete copy/delete of the file.
             This is slower but works even on file systems mounted remotely like nfs, samba or cifs.
         </td>
       </tr>
     </table>   

   </configuration>

   <see type="REQ">engine.runlevel</see>
   <author>laghi@swissinfo.org</author>
   <author>mr@marcelruff.info</author>
   <hacker>laghi@swissinfo.org</hacker>
   <date>2004 12 12</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.7 $</revision>
   <testcase status="CLOSED">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>-</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE">org.xmlBlaster.test.client.TestFilePollerPlugin</test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

