<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">


<requirement id='client.cpp.failsafe' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status='CLOSED'>
   <topic>
      The c++ client library supports failsafe reconnect where published messages are queued as long as
      the communication to xmlBlaster is broken.
   </topic>
   <description>
     <p>
     Hidden inside <b>ConnectionsHandler</b> there is a mechanism which in asynchronous way pings xmlBlaster
     to check if the communication is ok. When the ping fails, or when a request to xmlBlaster fails due
     to communication problems, the client library tries to reestablish the connection. This is done
     in an asynchronous way (an own thread in ConnectionHandler). While the library tries to
     reconnect all publish requests are queued on ram or persistently depending on the <code>queue/connection/type</code> configuration.<br/>
     Connect requests are queued too, provided you
     explicitly specify a public session id. When a connection request is queued, a faked
     ConnectReturnQos is returned to the client. Note that the private session id is missing but this does not
     create any problems since the client never uses it explicitly when invoking xmlBlaster (it is handled
     transparently and individually by the underlying communication protocols).
     </p>
     <p>
     For a detailed explication of the feature have a look at the specific requirement for
     <a href="./client.failsafe.html">failsafe reconnect</a>.
     </p>
     <p>
     You can register a listener to be instantly notified about the connection status changes.
     To do so the following methods must be implemented by the object implementing the I_ConnectionProblems
     interface. It is the object passed in the initFailsafe(...) method in XmlBlasterAccess.
     <ul>
     <li>bool reachedAlive(StatesEnum oldState, I_ConnectionsHandler* connectionsHandler)</li>
     <li>void reachedDead(StatesEnum oldState, I_ConnectionsHandler* connectionsHandler)</li>
     <li>void reachedPolling(StatesEnum oldState, I_ConnectionsHandler* connectionsHandler)</li>
     </ul>
     As the method names suggest, these notifications are invoked <b>after</b> the state of the connection
     has been taken place. So inside these methods the user can assume that the state of the 
     I_ConnectionHander is what the method name says (for example when reachedAlive is invoked, the state is
     already ALIVE).<br/>
     The reachedAlive method returns a bool. If you return <b>true</b> the queue will be flushed, i.e. the
     queue entries will be dispatched to xmlBlaster. If you return false, all queue entries will be 
     discarded.
     </p>
     If you don't invoke the method <b>initFailsafe</b> or if you pass to it a NULL pointer, then
     the failsafe mode and the described failsafe behavior runs silently in the client library.
     Note also that you must invoke <b>initFailsafe</b> before you invoke <b>connect</b>.
     <p><b>
     NOTE: To activate the failsafe mode you need to pass the command line parameter
     <code>-dispatch/connection/delay</code> with a value > 0. It is the sleeping
     interval in milliseconds between each reconnect retry. 5000 is a good value to start with.
     </b></p>
   </description>
   <example lang="CPP">
   <pre>

<![CDATA[

class HelloWorld2 : public I_Callback,         
                    public I_ConnectionProblems
{
   ......


   bool reachedAlive(StatesEnum, I_ConnectionsHandler*)
   {
      log_.info(ME, "reconnected");
      return true;
   }

   void reachedDead(StatesEnum, I_ConnectionsHandler*)
   {
      log_.info(ME, "lost connection");
   }

   void reachedPolling(StatesEnum, I_ConnectionsHandler*)
   {
      log_.info(ME, "going to poll modus");
   }

   ......


   void execute()
   {
      try {
         XmlBlasterAccess con(global_);

         // here you initialize the failsafe behaviour by giving
         // a pointer to the instance to notify when a state change
         // occcurs (which in this case is the 'this' object)

         con.initFailsafe(this);
         
         // do what you want to do here (connect publish subscribe)
         .....
   }

   string update(const string& sessionId, 
                 UpdateKey& updateKey, 
                 void *content, 
                 long contentSize, 
                 UpdateQos& updateQos)
   {
      log_.info(ME, "update: key: " + updateKey.toXml());
      log_.info(ME, "update: qos: " + updateQos.toXml());
      return "";
   }

};


]]>

   </pre>
   </example>

   <configuration where="client">
      <p><a NAME="config"></a></p>
      <p>
      These parameters allow to configure the C++-client on command line,
      over xmlBlaster.properties or over the environment (with lower priority):
      </p>
      <table border="1">
         <tr>
            <th>Property</th>
            <th>Default / Example</th>
            <th>Description</th>
            <th>Impl</th>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>-dispatch/connection/pingInterval</td>
            <td>10000</td>
            <td>Ping the server every given milliseconds</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>-dispatch/connection/retries</td>
            <td>-1</td>
            <td>How often to retry if connection fails (-1 is forever)
            </td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>-dispatch/connection/delay</td>
            <td>5000</td>
            <td>Delay between connection retries in milliseconds
                A delay value > 0 switches fails save mode on, 0 switches it off
            </td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

      </table>
   </configuration>

   <see type="REQ">client.cpp</see>
   <see type="REQ">client.cpp.queue</see>
   <see type="REQ">client.failsafe</see>

<!--   <see type="REQ">cluster</see> -->
   <author><a href="mailto:michele@laghi.eu">Michele Laghi</a></author>
   <date>2003 01 20</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.5 $</revision>
</requirement>

