<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='engine.persistence.subscription' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status="CLOSED">
   <topic>
      XmlBlaster supports sessions and subscriptions which persist a server crash.
   </topic>
   <description>
      <p>
      Persistent subscriptions will persist a server crash. After such a crash they are 
      reestablished during the recovery process. <br/>
      Subscription persistence is handled together with session persistence (subscription
      persistence would not work without session persistence). The SessionPersistencePlugin
      takes care of that.
      </p>
      <p>
      The recovery process must happen before the communication plugins are made available. 
      This to ensure that recovery will be accomplished completely before any client can 
      access xmlBlaster. It also must happen after the <code>TopicHandler</code> is 
      resuscitated.
      How to ensure this is described in the configuration section below. 
      </p>
      <p>
      A subscription is made persistent explicitly by passing the <code>persistent</code>
      flag in the subscribeQos. If the session to which it belongs is not persistent at the
      subscription time, it is implicitly made persistent by the subscrption.
      </p>
      <p>
      The benefit of having persistent subscriptions is that you as a client don't have
      to bother about resubscribing after a server crash. Since this is handled before any
      client is able to connect again (the configurator is responsible for that),
      gaps between possible publishes and subscriber reconnection are eliminated.
      <p>
      </p>
      Delivery of all publishes done before the subscriber can reconnect is thereby ensured.
      Currently there are some requisites which must be fulfilled to allow a subscription 
      to be made persistent. These are:
      <ul>
        <li>a) The session to which it belongs must be assigned by the client (i.e. he must 
          provide a <b>positive sessionId</b>)</li>
        <li>b) The <b>callback connection</b> must be configured as <b>failsafe</b> (to avoid 
             disconnection in cases where the client is inaccessible)</li>
      </ul>
      Some of the protocols may be less restrictive than others but if you fulfill the 
      mentioned requisites, subscription persistency will work on all communication protocols.
      </p>
      <p>
      Persistence of subscriptions is ensured by a persistent I_Map implementation. 
      Configuration of the storage (for example storage size or cache size) is done on server 
      side, either by passing parameters on the command line or in the xmlBlaster.properties 
      file.
      </p>
      <p><b>Exceptions:</b>
        <ul>
          <li>If the persistent subscription is done and the storage is overflown, an exception
              is thrown back to the client and the subscription is not valid.
          </li>
          <li>Making a persistent subscription on a transient session implies that the session
              is made persistent. If the storage for the persistent sessions is overflown, an
              exception is thrown back to the client.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
   </description>

   <example lang="Java">
     <pre>
      <![CDATA[
        ....
SubscribeQos qos = new SubscribeQos(global);
qos.setPersistent(true);
        ....
      ]]>
      </pre>
   </example>

   <example lang="XML">
     <pre>
      <![CDATA[
   <key queryType="XPATH">//airport</key>
   <qos><persistent>true</persistent></qos>
      ]]>
     </pre>
   </example>

   <configuration where="server">
      <p>
      The configuration of the plugin happens in the xmlBlasterPlugin.xml file.
      <pre>
      <![CDATA[
   <!--========== SubscriptionPersistencePlugin =============-->
    ....
   <plugin id='subPersistence' className='org.xmlBlaster.engine.SessionPersistencePlugin'>
      <action do='LOAD' onStartupRunlevel='3' sequence='1' />
      <action do='STOP' onShutdownRunlevel='2' sequence='6'/>
   </plugin>
    ....
      ]]>
      </pre>
      It is important that it is started <b>after runlevel 2</b> in order to assure that the topics
      are there when sessions and subscriptions are recovered. The logical place where to do
      it is on runlevel 3. Since this runlevel is the one on which communication plugins are
      loaded it is important that <b><code>subPersistence</code> is loaded before the communication
      plugins are</b> (by choosing a higher sequence number on load for the communication 
      plugins).<br/>
      The name <code>subPersitence</code> specified as the plugin id is not important since
      the plugin registers itself as a listener.
      </p>
      <p>
      <b><u>The configuration of the size of the storage</u></b><br/>
      All persistent subscriptions are stored on the same storage which is configurable on server
      side (the same way as the msgUnitStore and persistent sessions). You can either pass 
      the parameters in the <code>xmlBlaster.properties</code> file:
      <pre>
      ....
persistence/subscribe/maxEntriesCache = 10
persistence/subscribe/maxEntries = 200
      ....
    </pre>
      or on the command line when starting xmlBlaster:
      <pre>
   java org.xmlBlaster.Main \
   -persistence/subscribe/maxEntriesCache 10 \
   -persistence/subscribe/maxEntries 200
      </pre>
      </p>

   </configuration>
   <see type="REQ">client.failsafe</see>
   <see type="REQ">engine.persistence.session</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.engine.I_SessionPersistencePlugin</see>
   <author><a ref='michele@laghi.eu'>Michele Laghi</a></author>
   <hacker><a ref='michele@laghi.eu'>Michele Laghi</a></hacker>
   <date>2004 02 19</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.1 $</revision>
   <testcase status="CLOSED">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>-</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE">org.xmlBlaster.test.client.TestPersistentSession</test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

