<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='mom.publishsubscribe' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status='CLOSED'>
   <topic>XmlBlaster supports the publish/subscribe paradigm</topic>
   <description>
      <p>
      XmlBlaster allows clients to independently publish messages.
      Clients may subscribe independently to messages.
      </p>
      <p>
      The indirect communication, in particular the publish/subscribe communication model,
      is gaining increasing acceptance as a useful alternative to direct communication models,
      such as the ones based on remote invocations.
      </p>
      <p>
      The main advantage of this paradigm is that it supports a weak coupling among participants,
      which do not need to be aware of the location or number of its peers.
      This simplifies the reconfiguration of the applications and eases the reuse of the same components for different applications.
      </p>
      <p>
      One of the main advantages of the publish/subscribe model is that it decouples publishers
      and subscribers in several dimensions. Note these three dimensions of decoupling:
      <ul>
         <li>Space decoupling:<br />
          That captures the fact that interacting parties do not need to known each other</li>
         <li>Time decoupling:<br />
          That captures the fact that parties do not need to be actively participating in the interaction at the same time</li>
         <li>Flow decoupling:<br />
          That captures the asynchrony of the model</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
      Typically publish/subscribe behavior is configurable with quality-of-service (QoS) parameters,
      for example:
      <ul>
         <li>Message reliability</li>
         <li>Message expire time</li>
         <li>Message ordering</li>
         <li>Message priority</li>
         <li>Message filtering</li>
         <li>Message checking</li>
         <li>Message manipulation</li>
         <li>Message latency</li>
         <li>Message compression</li>
         <li>Routing of messages</li>
         <li>Readonly messages</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
   </description>
   <example lang="Java">
   </example>
   <configuration where="server">
   </configuration>
   <see type="REQ">engine.qos.publish.PubSub</see>
   <author>xmlBlaster@marcelruff.info</author>
   <date>2002 04 06</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.2 $</revision>
   <testcase status="OPEN">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>-</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE"></test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

