<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='msgDistributor.plugin' type='NEW' prio='LOW' status='CLOSED'>
   <topic>XmlBlaster has a plugin interface which allows to control the distribution of published
          messages to subscribers</topic>
   <description>
      <p>
      It is possible to let a plugin handle the distribution of published messages.
      The normal behavior is that all client-sessions subscribing to a certain topic are getting all 
      updates of that topic. This covers a wide range of use cases but sometimes it is just too 
      limiting.
      </p>
      <p>
      Suppose you want to guarantee that a published message is consumed once and only once. That 
      could be acheeved by sending a PtP message to a client (by specifying his session to avoid 
      double dispatching) and setting the message as volatile. This is great but it implies that the
      publisher knows the address of the client. What shall we do if the destination has to be 
      anonymous, i.e. if everybody is allowed to consume that message without the producer knowing 
      about it, as it is for example the case of queues in JMS ? 
      </p>
      <p>Suppose a load balancer is required where messages of the same topic have to be distributed
         <i>intelligently</i> among clients (for example by giving the current message to the client
         currently having the lowest cpu consumption)
      </p>
      <p>The mentioned cases are just a few of a whole spectra of potential -an many times specific-
         wishes users can have. A good approach to this problem is to avoid to hard-code 
         such specific cases and provide a plugin instead.
      </p>
      <p>The plugin controls the distribution of a published message to the subscribing clients, in
         other words it contains the logics which decide who/how a certain subscriber is getting a
         certain message or message update.
      </p>
      <p>
        There is a maximum of one plugin instance per TopicHandler instance. The Topic is the owner
        of the plugin. This implies that you define distribution control on a pro-topic base. 
        Practically this is defined in the PublishQos.
      </p>
      
      <h3>How to write my own plugin</h3>
      <p>
      As a plugin coder, you have to implement two interfaces
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li>I_Plugin: Which allows xmlBlaster to load the plugin</li>
         <li>I_MsgDistributor: Which forces you to implement some methods allowing you to control the 
             message flow, i.e. which addresses have to get the message and if/when/how the message 
             should be removed from the history queue.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
      This is simple and straightforward (see requirement msgDistributor.plugin.ConsumableQueuePlugin).
      </p>
      <p>
      Note that this is only an example of what you can do. The status message and priority 
      configuration of the above example is specific for exactly this plugin.
      If you implement your own plugin, you can do whatever you like.
      </p>
      <p>
      For the mentioned example of only once delivery an implementation exists which you can 
      use/change and modify according to your needs. It is the <i>ConsumableQueuePlugin</i> 
      (see link below).
      </p>
   </description>
   <configuration where="server">
<!--
   -queue/callback/maxBytes
                       The maximum size in bytes of the storage [10485760].
   -queue/callback/maxBytesCache.
                       The maximum size in bytes in the cache [2097152].
   -queue/callback/onOverflow
                       What happens if storage is full [deadMessage]
   -queue/callback/onFailure
                       Error handling when storage failed [deadMessage]
   -queue/callback/type
                       The plugin type [CACHE]
   -queue/callback/version
                       The plugin version [1.0]
   -queue/callback/defaultPlugin
                       The plugin type,version (short form) [CACHE,1.0]
-->
     <p>
       The first step to do when configuring this plugin is to register it by assigning a name to it.
       This is normally put into the xmlBlaster.properties file which is read by the server.
       The name has the structure <code>PluginType[instanceName][instanceVersion]</code> as stated in the
       first row in the table below. Besides the class name of the implementation to use you could
       also pass properties which are specific to the given implementation. <br/>
       The second step is to define a default plugin to be used when the client does not specify
       anything explicitly. This is done as in the third row of the table below.
      </p>
      <center>
      <table border="1" width="75%">
         <tr>
            <th>Property</th>
            <th>Default / Example</th>
            <th>Description</th>
            <th>Implemented</th>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>MsgDistributorPlugin[MyPlugin][1]</td>
            <td>com.xy.MyPlugin</td>
            <td>Register your plugin</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>MsgDistributorPlugin[Another][1.0]</td>
            <td>com.xy.MySpecial</td>
            <td>Register your plugin</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>MsgDistributorPlugin/defaultPlugin</td>
            <td>"MyPlugin,1" or "Another,1.0" or "undef"</td>
            <td>Specifiy the plugin to use as a default.<br />
                Default is <i>undef</i> that is no default plugin is loaded which is usually the correct setting:<br />
                The client normally chooses on publish its desired plugin by specifying it in the topic section of 
                the publish QoS</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>
      </table>
      </center>
      <p>
      When publishing a topic for the first time (or when doing an administrative publish), you can
      specify which plugin to use for the distribution of the message. In java you would do it like this:
<pre>

   ...

   PublishQos pubQos = new PublishQos(global);
   TopicProperty topicProp = new TopicProperty(global);
   topicProp.setMsgDistributor("ConsumableQueue,1.0");
   pubQos.setTopicProperty(topicProp);
   MsgUnit msgUnit = new MsgUnit(new PublishKey(global, someOid), 
                                 someContent, 
                                 pubQos);
   global.getXmlBlasterAccess().publish(msgUnit);

   ...

</pre>
      </p>
      <!-- p>
      For coding and configuration of plugins please read the
      requirement msgDistributor.plugin.ConsumableQueue (see link below)
      </p -->
   </configuration>

   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.engine.distributor.I_MsgDistributor</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.engine.distributor.plugins.ConsumableQueuePlugin</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.plugin.I_Plugin</see>
   <see type="REQ">msgDistributor.plugin.ConsumableQueue</see>
   <see type="REQ">util.property.env</see>
   <author><a href="mailto:michele@laghi.eu">Michele Laghi</a></author>
   <date>2003 10 16</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.4 $</revision>
   <testcase status="CLOSED">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>-</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE">org.xmlBlaster.test.distributor.TestConsumableQueue</test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

