<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='admin.jmx' type='NEW' prio='MEDIUM' status='INWORK'>

   <topic>XmlBlaster provides an JMX-Interface for monitoring and controlling</topic>

   <description>
      JMX-support (Java Management Extension for J2EE) has been added to xmlBlaster.<br />
      On startup a small JMX-Server is started.<p />
      <b>What is JMX?</b><br />
      JMX is a new Sun standard that allows Java developers to rapidly management
      functionality into existing applications.<br />
      JMX defines a standard for writing JMX objects, also called MBeans.
      MBeans basically represent the state and the functionality of a managed ressource.
      It is possible for a JMX client to invoke methods and access attributes on an MBean.
      A JMX Agent enables manageability of these functionalities from local or remote,
      allowing a system administrator to manage the components of the application.
      <br />
      In order to gain access to ressources from JMX-management,
      it is neccessary to implement a JMX-compliant interface.
      These interfaces are charatericed by the postposition "MBean" in the interface name.
      <br />
      Taken for example is org.xmlBlaster.engine.RequestBroker. A RequestBrokerMBean Interface has been
      added. This MBean is loaded at startup.
      When you point your browser to: http://hostname:8082 you will see the output of
      a JMX-Http-Adaptor.
      <p />
      <b>Custom protocol adaptors</b><br />
      The JMX framework allows to add protocol adaptors/connectors like the http-adaptor
      to the framework without disturbing the instrumentation.
      <br />
      Such an adaptor is implemented too. It is a xmlBlaster-adaptor.
      This adaptor is running on port 3424.
      The adaptor enables the communication with the JMX-Server across the network.
      Within the "normal" xmlBlaster-Instance another embedded xmlBlasterinstance is started
      that handles the communication with clients.
      <p />
      <b>Administration-client</b>
      <br />
      An administration-client that uses this new feature has been added.
      It can be found at org.xmlBlaster.jmxgui.<br />
      The Userinterface is pluggable and new plugins, handling other MBeans, can be
      added to the system.
      To show the usage, two plugins have already been added.

   </description>

   <todo type="HTML">
    <ol>
      <li>Write some TestCase!</li>
      <li>Strip down embedded XmlBlaster to minimum</li>
      <li>Write some Plugins</li>
    </ol>
   </todo>

   <see type="REQ">admin.commands</see>



   <author>oliver.neubert@doubleslash.de</author>
   <date>2003 06 10</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.1 $</revision>

   <testcase status="OPEN">
      <name></name>
      <comment>
      </comment>
      <test tool="SUITE"></test>
   </testcase>

</requirement>
