<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='cluster.dirtyRead' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status="CLOSED">
   <topic>A cluster slave node can directly cache published messages</topic>
   <description>
      <p>
      Usually if you publish a message to a cluster slave node, the message
      is directly forwarded and routed to the master node of this message type.
      </p>
      <p>
      If clients connected to frodo (a slave node) subscribe to messages frodo
      subscribes it from heron, as heron is the master. Only messages coming from
      the master are approved. The slaves receives the update and
      delivers it to the client:
      </p>
      <p>
      <img src="cluster-noDirtyRead-sequence.gif" />
      </p>
      <p>
      It is possible to suppress the update (2.1.1) as the slave
      can just as well dirty read the published message at step (2):
      </p>
      <p>
      <img src="cluster-dirtyRead-sequence.gif" />
      </p>
      <p>
      The main reason for this requirement is to minimize net traffic on
      connections between cluster nodes with limited band width.<br />
      For example if you send 1200 radar messages / sec over a 2MBit net
      the band width is almost exhausted. With dirty reads you can allow the cluster
      slave to cache those messages directly without approving from the master node
      and updating back again (assuming you have local subscribers at the slave node).
      </p>
   </description>


   <example lang="XML" type="HTML">
   </example>

   <configuration where="server">
   <p>
   The dirty read attribute has to be set at all stratum levels to be active, here
   <code>heron</code> declares it (he is the master):
   </p>
<pre>
<![CDATA[
cluster.node[heron.mycomp.com]=\
   <clusternode id='heron.mycomp.com'>\
      <master type='DomainToMaster' dirtyRead='true'>\
         <key queryType='DOMAIN' domain='RUGBY_NEWS'/>\
      </master>\
   </clusternode>
]]>
</pre>
   <p>
   and <code>frodo</code> as a slave will dirty read messages
   of the domain RUGBY_NEWS.
   </p>
   <p>
   See xmlBlaster/demo/javaclients/cluster for more examples.
   </p>
   </configuration>

   <see type="REQ">cluster</see>

   <author>xmlBlaster@marcelruff.info</author>
   <date>2002 06 12</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.8 $</revision>
   <testcase status="CLOSED">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>Tests a cluster setup as described in this requirement</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE">org.xmlBlaster.test.cluster.DirtyReadTest</test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

