<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='mime.plugin.publishfilter' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status='CLOSED'>
   <topic>XmlBlaster has a MIME based plugin interface to filter, check or manipulate published messages</topic>
   <description>
      <p>
      XmlBlaster allows you to publish messages.
      Sometimes you may need to check messages before you accept them. Another use case
      could be that you want to manipulate message contents when they arrive at xmlBlaster.
      </p>
      <p>
      These are use cases where you may want to write a little plugin, allowing to
      intercept messages when they are published to xmlBlaster.
      With such a plugin you are able to add some business logic natively to the otherwise generic
      xmlBlaster core.
      </p>
      <img src="mimePublishFilter.gif" border="0" title="XmlBlaster publish MIME plugin example" alt="Example how to use the publish MIME plugin" />
      <p>
      As a plugin coder, you have to implement two interfaces
      <ul>
         <li>I_Plugin: Which allows xmlBlaster to load the plugin</li>
         <li>I_PublishFilter: Which forces you to implement the intercept() method</li>
      </ul>
      This is simple and straight forward (see requirement mime.plugin.publishfilter.howto).
      </p>
      <p>
      Filter Features:
      </p>
      <ul>

      <li>MIME based plugin selection<br />
      The plugin you code has to supply MIME types which it can handle. Only messages of this
      mime type are directed to the plugin. The mime type "*" registers the plugin for
      all message MIME types.
      </li>

      <li>The filter intercepts published messages<br />
      When a client invokes publish() to send a message to xmlBlaster, the message
      calls the appropriate plugin when it arrives in the server.<br />
      This happens before xmlBlaster checks if it needs to be sent to another cluster node
      and before xmlBlaster stores or processes it.<br />
      Publish/Subscribe and PtP messages are equally checked.<br />
      If the plugin is registered for all mime types with "*", internal messages are send
      to the filter as well, usually you should just ignore
      them (see example in PublishLenFilter).
      </li>

      <li>Allowed actions with a message<br />
      You may do following actions with the new message:
      <ol>
         <li>Accept the message<br />
            Return values null, "" or "OK" accept the message</li>
         <li>Reject the message<br />
            All other returned strings will reject the message and send
            the given string back to the publisher. For example a return value
            like "REJECTED" will be delivered as "&lt;qos>&lt;state id='REJECTED'/>&lt;/qos>"
            to the publisher, which is the return value of the publish() invocation.</li>
         <li>Modify the message<br />
            The plugin may manipulate the content of the message if desired,
            delivering changed content to xmlBlaster. Changing of the key or qos is not allowed,
            as the problems which may ocure are not analyzed yet.</li>
      </ol>
      </li>

      <li>Multiple filters per mime type<br />
      Multiple filter plugins can be specified for each published message.
      They are sequentially executed and if
      one filter rejects (the intercept() method returns no "" or "OK") the message
      is not accepted. The filters are logically AND connected.
      </li>

      <li>Filter in cluster environment<br />
      The filter is applied before the message is forwarded from a slave
      node to its master node. So you can suppress cluster messages in the slave
      already.
      </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
      </p>
   </description>
   <example lang="XML" type="HTML">
      <p>
         This is an example message for a publish() method invocation:
      </p>
      <table border="1"><tr><td><pre>
&lt;key oid='LongMessage'/>
content="veeerrrrrylongcooontenttttttt"
&lt;qos/>
      </pre></td></tr></table>
      <p>
         As the message is too long for our plugin, the plugin.intercept() method
         returns "TOOLONG".
         xmlBlaster rejects the messages and returns for this publish()
      </p>
      <table border="1"><tr><td><pre>
&lt;qos>&lt;state id='TOOLONG'/>&lt;qos>
      </pre></td></tr></table>

      <p>
         If you return strings contain '&lt;' characters, please
         embrace your return value with a &lt;![CDATA[ ... ]]&gt; section.
      </p>
   </example>

   <example lang="any" type="HTML">
      <p>
      Here are some typical use cases why to write a plugin:
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li>
          A publish plugin could for example eliminate identical messages.<br />
          Imagine that multiple radar stations track the same
          air plane.
          You could use the plugin to filter them and only pass one radar
          position of the same air plane further.
         </li>

         <li>
            Another use case could be to reject messages which are to big,
            or you could write a regex plugin and reject messages
            with unwanted content.
         </li>

         <li>
            Use the plugin for mime conversion (1).<br />
            Imagine you receive documents in different formats like
            Staroffice, Winword etc.<br />
            You could write a little plugin for those mime types
            and convert all messages to PDF or into some XML esperanto
            format.
         </li>

         <li>
            Use the plugin for mime conversion (2).<br />
            Imagine you receive air pressure values in different units like
            HPascal, Newton/sqare-millimeter, mbar, mm of mercury.<br />
            You could write a little plugin for those mime types
            and convert all messages to standardized HPascal.
         </li>
      </ul>
   </example>

   <configuration where="server">
      <p>
      For coding and configuration of plugins please read the
      requirement mime.plugin.publishfilter.howto (see link below)
      </p>
   </configuration>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.engine.mime.I_PublishFilter</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.engine.mime.demo.PublishLenChecker</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.plugin.I_Plugin</see>
   <see type="REQ">mime.plugin.publishfilter.howto</see>
   <see type="REQ">util.property.env</see>
   <see type="REQ">mime.plugin.accessfilter</see>
   <author>xmlBlaster@marcelruff.info</author>
   <date>2002 03 14</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.13 $</revision>
   <testcase status="CLOSED">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>-</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE">org.xmlBlaster.test.mime.TestPublishFilter</test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

