<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='protocol.local' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status="CLOSED">
   <topic>XmlBlaster supports native client server communication in the same JVM</topic>
   <description>
      <p>
      It is possible to start xmlBlaster clients with the runlevel manager of xmlBlaster.
      Like this the client is started on xmlBlaster startup in the same JVM as the server
      in a configurable sequence with other services (see our runlevel manager requirement).
      </p>
      <p>
      If a client connects to XmlBlaster with the <code>XmlBlasterAccess</code> client interface
      it can choose the communication protocol like Corba, SOCKET, XmlRpc and more.
      But if the client runs in the same JVM we can avoid the communication over a socket
      by choosing the <b>LOCAL</b> protocol plugin. This improves speed and 
      avoids using OS resources like ports and threads.<br />
      Switching the protocol is just a configuration setting, so any existing
      client can choose to communicate locally. Note that the client must implement the
      <code>I_Plugin</code> interface to be loadable as a plugin, this is described in
      the <i>engine.runlevel</i> requirement.
      </p>
   </description>
   <example lang="Java">
   </example>

   <configuration where="client">
      <p>On <b>client side</b> we need to register the <b>LOCAL</b> protocol
      plugin to be available in the Java client library.
      </p>
      <table border="1">
         <tr>
            <th>Property</th>
            <th>Default / Example</th>
            <th>Description</th>
            <th>Implemented</th>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>ClientProtocolPlugin[LOCAL][1.0]</td>
            <td>org.xmlBlaster.client.protocol.local.LocalConnection</td>
            <td>Specify the plugin to get support of direct client/server communication
            in the same JVM
            </td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>ClientCbServerProtocolPlugin[LOCAL][1.0]</td>
            <td>org.xmlBlaster.client.protocol.local.LocalCallbackImpl</td>
            <td>Specify the native callback plugin
                </td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

      </table>
   </configuration>
   <todo type="HTML">
   <ol>
      <li>
      </li>
   </ol>
   </todo>
   <see type="REQ">protocol</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.client.protocol.local.LocalConnection</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.client.protocol.local.LocalCallbackImpl</see>
   <see type="API">javaclients.HelloWorldLocal</see>
   <author>xmlBlaster@marcelruff.info</author>
   <date>2003 06 28</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.1 $</revision>
   <testcase status="OPEN">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>-</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE">testsuite.</test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

