<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">


<requirement id='queue' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status='CLOSED'>
   <topic>
      Within XmlBlaster there is a complete queue framework offering
      generic plugin based storage. The queues can be <b>persistent</b> or
      <b>transient</b>.
   </topic>
   <description>
     <p>Queues can (and are) used in different parts in xmlBlaster. On client side
      they are used to store the messages waiting to be delivered to xmlBlaster.
      This is commonly the case when the communication between client and server
      is temporarily down.</p>
      <p>On the server side there are callback queues (also called update queues) to
      <b>temporarily</b> store messages waiting to be delivered, for example callbacks to client
      subscriptions or PtP messages, or to <b>persistently</b> store the messages in order
      to be able to recover after a server crash.</p>
      <p>Another usage of queues within xmlBlaster is the storage of the history of
      messages, i.e. to store several <i>publishes</i> made on the same message-<i>oid</i>.</p>
      <p>Queues are also used as swapping devices to free memory when memory consumption
      is high.</p>
      <p>The different queue implementations used within xmlBlaster are plugins, so if you want some 
      specific feature, or if you want to implement your own queue, this can be done.</p>
      <p>Queue entries have priorities (from 0 to 9) and a guaranteed order of delivery within the same 
      priority. This means that messages are sorted primary by priority: higher priority messages are the 
      first ones extracted by a take, peek or remove action. The second ordering criteria applied is the 
      uniqueId of the entry. The lower uniqueId are returned first (since normally this uniqueId is
      related to the timestamp, older entries are returned first).</p>
      
   </description>

    <example lang="Java" type="HTML">
       These are example QoS of subscribe() invocations:
       <pre>
&lt;qos>
   &lt;queue maxEntries='10000' maxBytes='1000000000' onOverflow='deadMessage'/>
&lt;/qos>
       </pre>
   </example>
   <configuration where="server">

        <p>
      These parameters allow to configure the queues.
      </p>
      <table border="1">
         <tr>
            <th>Property</th>
            <th>Default</th>
            <th>Description</th>
            <th>Hot</th>
            <th>Impl</th>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>queue/defaultPlugin</td>
            <td>CACHE,1.0</td>
            <td>specifies the type (or the alias name) and version of the plugin to be used as default if nothing else is specified</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>QueuePlugin [CACHE][1.0]</td>
            <td>org.xmlBlaster. util.queue.cache. CacheQueueInterceptorPlugin</td>
            <td>specifies the class to be used for this particular queue plugin (in this case the plugin offering caching facilities)</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>queue/maxEntries</td>
            <td>1000</td>
            <td>specifies the maximum number of entries allowed in this queue (if it is a persistent queue)</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
            <td>queue/maxEntriesCache</td>
            <td>1000</td>
            <td>specifies the maximum number of entries allowed in this queue (if the queue is a memory based queue like RAM queues)</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>

         <tr>
            <td>queue/maxBytes</td>
            <td>10485760</td>
            <td>(10 MB) specifies the maximum total size in Bytes allowed for this queue (if it is a persistent queue)</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>
         <tr>
            <td>queue/maxBytesCache</td>
            <td>2097152</td>
            <td>(2MB) specifies the maximum total size allowed in this queue (if the queue is a memory based queue like RAM queues)</td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
            <td><img src="ok.gif" border="0" alt="yes" /></td>
         </tr>
        </table>
   </configuration>

   <see type="REQ">queue.cache</see>
   <see type="REQ">queue.jdbc.commontable</see>
   <see type="REQ">queue.ram</see>
   <see type="REQ">queue.jdbc.oracle</see>
   <see type="REQ">queue.jdbc.postgres</see>
   <see type="REQ">queue.jdbc.sqlserver</see>
   <see type="REQ">client.c.queue</see>
   <see type="REQ">client.cpp.queue</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.queue.I_Queue</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.queue.QueuePluginManager</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.queue.I_QueueEntry</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.qos.storage.QueuePropertyBase</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.I_Plugin</see>
   <see type="API">org.xmlBlaster.util.Global</see>

<!--   <see type="REQ">cluster</see> -->
   <author>laghi@swissinfo.org</author>
   <date>2002 11 15</date>
   <revision>$Revision: 1.13 $</revision>
   <testcase status="CLOSED">
      <name>-</name>
      <comment>-</comment>
      <test tool="SUITE">org.xmlBlaster.test.classtest.queue.I_QueueTest</test>
      <test tool="SUITE">org.xmlBlaster.test.classtest.queue.JdbcQueueTest</test>
   </testcase>
</requirement>

