<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE requirement SYSTEM "requirement.dtd">

<requirement id='security.introduction' type='NEW' prio='HIGH' status='CLOSED'>
   <topic>HOWTO: xmlBlaster Security Introduction</topic>
   <description>
      <h1>Introduction</h1>
      
      <h2>Why Security?</h2>
      <p>
         Information security became over the years a more and more important 
         topic. First, it was of interest only for military and secret service 
         organisations. But the more information systems like computers concern 
         everybodies life and these systems become interconnected, the higher is
         the importance of security for everyone. It doesn't matter if it is
         the army, a commercial organisation or even a private user, security is
         an essential topic.
      </p>
              
      <h2>What is Security?</h2>
      <p>
         After the dozens of books written on the subject, it's hard to 
         understand that a common definition of security doesn't exist.<br />
      
      
         The attempt to find a definition including all aspect of security
         results in quiet woolly definition like the following, which we
         will use now:
      </p>
      <p>
      <ul>
         Security refers to the possibility of a system, to protect its
         objects regarding <i>confidentiality</i> and <i>integrity</i>.
      </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
         In this context confidentiality and integrity are defined as:
      </p>
      
         <ul>
            <li>
               <b>Confidentiality:</b><br />
               "The property that information is not made available or disclosed
                to unauthorized individuals, entities, or processes." [RFC2828]
            </li>     
            <li>
               <b>Integrity:</b><br />
               "The property that data have not been changed, destroyed, or
                lost in an unauthorized or accidental manner." [RFC2828]
            </li>
         </ul>
      
      <p>
         Both are the <i>primary goals</i> of security. To reach them, it is often
         necessary to reach subsequent goals. These additional goals are often
         called <i>secondary goals</i>. Examples are:
      </p>
      <p>
         <ul>
            <li>accountability</li>
            <li>non-repudiation</li>
            <li>privacy</li>
            <li>anonymity</li>
            <li>and many more.</li>
         </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
      Some of them seem to be incompatible (e.g. accountability and anonymity),
      but all are more or less important for a secure system. This shows two 
      things:
      </p>
      <p>
         <ol>
            <li>
               The meaning of security can differ from case to case, because the goals
               may have a different weight.
            </li>
            <li>
               A 100% secure system is impossible. 
            </li>
         </ol>
      </p>
      <p>
      <b>An example:</b><br/>
      In an electronic voting system each voter can vote for something /
      somebody. In this case the voter has the following understanding of
      security:
      </p> 
      <ul>
         <li>
            The system must ensure that the vote is counted correctly
            (nothing/nobody else should be able to generate a vote with a wrong
            identity, to change or hold back a correct vote) [integrity]
         </li>
         <li>   
            Nothing and nobody (even not the voting system) must be able
            to determine who voted for whom/what. [-> confidentiality (+ anonymity)]
         </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
         The voting system has a slightly different understanding of security.
         In addition, it must ensure that everybody has only a single vote. 
         Everybody must be accountable for its actions. But this collides
         with the voters desire of anonymity. Both are not compatible without
         lowering one's sights.
      </p>
<!--   <h1>Threads</h1>
      <p>   
         ===
      </p>
-->
   <h1>Goals</h1>
      <p>
         The xmlBlaster security system should address the main aspects of security as mentioned above. 
         But because of the fact that a 100% secure system, covering all issues won't be me more than a nice 
         illusion. A security serving system for the xmlBlaster cannot be more than model and a framework.
         Its main goal is to support all actions (in general: intercepting the flow of actions and information)
         required by the real implementation of software components (called 'plugins') to enforce the 
         respective meaning of security.
       </p>
   <h1>Terms</h1>
   <p>(Session, Subject, Right, Role, Group, Security, Identity, Authentication, Authorization, Access Control (AC), Message Protection, ...)</p>
</description>
<see type='REQ'>security.development.serverPlugin.howto</see>
<see type="REQ">security.htpasswd</see>
<see type="REQ">security.ldap</see>
<see type="REQ" label="SOCKET based SSL protection">protocol.socket</see>
<!-- see type='REQ'>security.development.clientPlugin.howto</see>
<see type='REQ'>security.administration.howto</see -->
</requirement>
